A Guide to the William Henry Fitzhugh Payne Papers, 1786-1910
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
William Henry Fitzhugh Payne Papers, 1786-1910
The Library of Virginia
21705
.15 cubic feet
William Henry Fitzhugh Payne
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Purchased from Harry Harris, Richmond, Virginia, 25 April 1940.
Biographical Information
William Henry Fitzhugh Payne was born 27 January 1830 in Fauquier County, Virginia to Arthur Alexander Morson Payne (1804-1868) and Mary Conway Mason Fitzhugh Payne (1805-1842). Educated at the University of Missouri, the University of Virginia, and the Virginia Military Institute, Payne practiced law and became Commonwealth's attorney for Fauquier County. He married Mary Elizabeth Winston on 29 September 1852. Upon the outbreak of the Civil War, Payne entered Confederate service as captain of the Black Horse Cavalry, was promoted to major of the 4th Virginia Cavalry September 1861, to lieutenant-colonel in 1862 of the 4th Virginia cavalry, and finally to brigadier-general commanding Payne's Brigade, Fitzhugh Lee's Division and served under Jubal Early in the Shenandoah Valley. Payne was wounded at the battle of Williamsburg on 5 May 1862, and at Five Forks, 1 April 1865. Captured after Williamsburg and the day before Gettysburg, he was exchanged both times. Payne was last captured 13 April 1865 and taken to Washington DC. After his release, Payne returned to Fauquier County and his position as Commonwealth's attorney, which he held until 1869. Payne later practiced law in Warrenton, Virginia, and Washington DC and served as counsel for the Southern Railway. He also served as president of the Association of the Army of Northern Virginia, Virginia division and was a member of the Veteran Cavalry Association, Army of Northern Virginia. Payne died in Washington 29 March 1904, and was buried in the Warrenton, Virginia, cemetery.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1786-1910, of William Henry Fitzhugh Payne (1830-1904) of Fauquier County, Virginia, consist of correspondence, military commissions and orders, newspaper clippings, and telegrams concerning cavalry operations, duels and duelling, and politics. Also includes a speech by Payne nominating Fitzhugh Lee (1835-1905) for governor of Virginia, a eulogy by Payne for his brother Alexander Dixon Payne (1837-1893), and reminiscences of Payne's wife, Mary Elizabeth Winston Payne (1831-1920), titled "Search for My Wounded Husband." Also includes a membership certificate for the Veteran Cavalry Association of the Army of Northern Virginia, located in oversize.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Payne Family Papers, 1879-1898 (LVA accession 30884).
Contents List
- Entry, 8 March 1786, by William Payne for 4800 acres of land based on various military warrants. Copy. (Folder 1)
- Land grant, 27 November 1787, for 1600 acres in the Military District to William Payne from Governor Edmund Randolph. Copy. (Folder 1)
- Land grant, 27 November 1787, for 1600 acres in the Military District to William Payne from Governor Edmund Randoph. Copy. (Folder 1)
- Land grant, 27 November 1787, for 1600 in the Military District to William Payne from Governor Edmund Randolph. Copy. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 5 April 1854, William Henry Fitzhugh Payne, Warrenton, to Robert Smith concerning concerning the difficulties between Nathaniel Tyler and Richard M. Smith. Includes notes on the matter. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 7 July 1860, James M. Smith, Alexandria, Virginia, to Payne stating that he would like to settle the differences between them and forget the past. Includes note by Payne explaining reasons for the letter. (Folder 1)
- Commission, 10 May 1861, for Payne as Captain of 2nd regiment of cavalry, 5th brigade, 2nd division of Virginia miliatia by Governor John Letcher of Virginia. Payne's qualification for the commission noted by L. B. Butler, 14 May 1861. (Folder 1)
- Commission, 11 September 1861, for Payne as major of cavalry in the active volunteer forces of Virginia, by Governor John Letcher. Payne's qualification noted by William W. Elzey, 23 September 1861. (Folder 1)
- Special orders No. 276, 12 September 1861, from George Deas, A.A.G., Adjutant and Inspector General's Office, assigning Payne to duty with the 4th Virginia Cavalry. (Folder 1)
- Telegram, 2 October 1862, from Henry Shackelford, Culpeper, Virginia, to Payne, reporting that about fifty Union soldiers have been seen near Stevensburg, Virginia. (Folder 1)
- Appointment, 20 October 1862, of Payne as lieutenant colonel of the 4th Virginia Cavalry, by Confederate President Jefferson Davis, through Secretary of War, George W. Randolph, Richmond, Virginia. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 22 February 1863, from General Jeb Stuart to Payne, Lynchburg, Virginia, stating that he intends to assign Payne to establish and command a camp for paroled prisoners. Includes a memorandum from Stuart containing guidelines for this endeavor. (Folder 1)
- Telegram, 4 March 1863, from Stuart to Payne revoking his letter of 22 February concerning Payne and the paroled prisoners camp. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 4 March 1863, from Stuart to Payne explaining why Stuart had intended to assign Payne to head up the paroled prisoners camp. (Folder 1)
- Special Orders no. 37, 2 September 1864, from headquarters, Cavalry Forces, Valley Department, Major General Fitz Lee through Major J. D. Ferguson assigning Colonel Payne to the temporary command of [General Lunsford Lindsay] Lomax's (Old) Brigade. Reverse side contains a letter, 4 September 1864, from Payne to his wife. (Folder 1)
- Appointment, 4 November 1864, William H. Payne as brigadier-general in the Provisional Army, C.S.A., by President Davis through Secretary of War James A. Seddon. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 11 November 1864, Lieutenant General Jubal A. Early to Payne ordering him to move his command to find the enemy. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 24 December 1864, from General Thomas T. Munford, headquarters, Wickham's Brigade, Charlottesville, Virginia, to Payne explaining why he will not accept Payne's challenge to a duel. Includes note by Payne concerning his reply. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 9 February 1866, from Lieutenant W. A. MacNulty, Acting Provost Marshall, U.S. Army, Warrenton, to Payne, Warrenton, requesting a statement from Payne concerning a complaint by Samuel Williams, an African American, that Payne had pulled a revolver on him. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 9 February 1866, from Payne to Lieutenant MacNulty replying that Williams had knocked his son down and cursed at him. Payne states that he was protecting his son. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 10 February 1866, from Lieutenant MacNulty to Payne concerning the confrontation between Payne and Williams and MacNulty's decision. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 4 September 1866, from Payne to B. H. Shackelford requesting Shackelford to explain earlier remarks. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 5 September 1866 from B. H. Shackelford to Payne clarifying his previous remarks to Payne. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 5 September 1866, from Payne to Shackelford stating that Shackelford's reply was satisfactory. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 12 February 1867, from Thomas L. Rosser, Baltimore, Maryland, to Payne commenting on an attack in the press on Rosser by John Singleton Mosby, and asking Payne's help in discovering why. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 23 February 1867, from Thomas L. Rosser, Baltimore, to Payne stating that he had written John S. Mosby concerning his printed attack, but has not heard anything return. Rosser adds that he is gathering facts and information to defend himself from such attacks. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 23 February 1867 from Jubal Early, Toronto, Canada, to Payne concerning Early's military career during the Civil War. (Folder 1)
- Note, 23 May 1871, from Payne to Rice W. Payne demanding an apology for Rice Payne's "conduct and language" toward him. (Folder 2)
- Agreement, 23 May 1871, drawn up by B. P. Noland and Eppa Hunton on behalf of Rice Payne and William H. Payne settling their dispute. (Folder 2)
- Letter, 23 May 1872, from Fitzhugh Lee, Richmond, to Payne, Warrenton, commenting on the Civil War and the Confederate cavalry, as well as personal matters. (Folder 2)
- Letter, [1873], from J. D. Carter to Payne demanding an explantation of remarks by Payne that Carter believed insulted Carter's father. Includes reply from Payne, as well as Payne's comments on the situation. (Folder 2)
- Petition, [1873?], of William R. Trigg, William B. Tabb, William L. Royall, and John L. Meredith to the Fauquier County Circuit Court seeking a writ of habeas corpus in relation to murder charges stemming from their roles in a duel between Page McCarty and John B. Mordecai. (Folder 2)
- Article, 20 May 1873, on the duel between Page McCarty and John B. Mordecai, in the Richmond Enquirer. (Folder 2)
- Letter, 17 June 1873, from Bradley T. Johnson, Richmond, to Payne regarding the McCarty-Mordecai duel. (Folder 2)
- Letter, 4 August 1874, from John S. Mosby, Warrenton, to G. B. Samuels, commenting on state politics. Includes a note by J. A. Settle to Thomas Smith, verifying Mosby's letter and adding a comment, as well as Smith's verification. There are two copies of this letter and notes. In one, Settle is incorrectly identified as J. A. Samuels. (Folder 2)
- Letter, 19 August 1874, from Charles H. Gowan[?] to Payne recounting the differences between Lyttleton S. Helm and [J. H.?] Williams, as well as politics. (Folder 2)
- Letter, 20 August 1874, from C. M. Smith, Upperville, Virginia, to Payne, Warrenton, concerning John S. Mosby's political maneuverings. (Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 20-21 August 1874, between John S. Mosby, A.D. Payne and others regarding a proposed duel between Mosby and Payne. (Folder 2)
- Article, 24 August 1874, concerning the proposed duel between John S. Mosby and Alexander Dixon Payne, in the Alexandria Virginia Sentinel. (Folder 2)
- Memorandum, 27 August 1874, by William H. Payne on the proposed Mosby-A. D. Payne duel, including clippings. (Folder 2)
- Letter, 15 October 1876, from John S. Mosby to Lyttleton S. Helm inquiring if Helm accused Mosby of being a traitor to his country. (Folder 2)
- Letter, 15 October 1876, from Lyttelton S. Helm to John S. Mosby replying to Mosby's charge that Helm called him a traitor to his country. (Folder 2)
- Speech, 11 August 1877, Remarks of General W. H. Payne of Fauquier Nominating General Fitz Lee for Governor, Richmond State. (Folder 2)
- Letter, 20 August 1877, from F. E. Shepperd, Warrenton, to Payne giving Shepperd's opinion of the actions of James V. Brooke. (Folder 2)
- Letter, 20 August 1877, from R. H. Downman to Payne regarding to remarks about Payne supposedly made by James V. Brooke. Includes letter, 20 August 1877, from Brooke to Payne disavowing having made any remarks about Payne. (Folder 2)
- Letter, 21 August 1877, from Payne, Warrenton, to James V. Brooke accepting Brooke's disclaimer. (Folder 2)
- Letter, [13?] June 1878, from Robert R. Campbell to Payne concerning a challenge between Charles Daniel, [James C.] Scott, and himself. (Folder 2)
- Statement, [June 1878], of Eppa Hunton, Jr., to Payne concerning the difficulty between Robert R. Campbell and James C. Scott. This item was originally considered to be connected to a later confrontation in 1881 between Campbell and Scott, but further investigation indicates that it refers to the June 1878 confrontation. (Folder 2)
- Opinion, 13 June 1878, of William H. Payne concerning the difficulty between Robert Campbell and James C. Scott. This item was originally considered to be connected to a later confrontation in 1881 between Campbell and Scott, but further investigation indicates that it refers to the June 1878 confrontation. (Folder 2)
- Letter, 1 August 1878, from Payne to the editor of the Alexandria Sunday Bulletin asking for the identities of correspondents who made statements offensive to Payne. (Folder 2)
- Letter, 2 August 1878, from Thomas A. [Brown?], editor of the Sunday Bulletin, to Payne respectfully declining to provide the names and adding that they meant no personal offense towards Payne. (Folder 2)
- Letter, 2 August 1878, from Payne to the editor of the Sunday Bulletin accepting his statement. (Folder 2)
- Memorandum, 23 September 1878, concerning the differences between S. P. Bailey and John S. Mosby, possibly made by William H. Payne. (Folder 2)
- Clipping, 16 October 1876, from the Richmond State containing correspondence between James Kemper and William Mahone which almost resulted in a duel. (Folder 2)
- Letter, 31 December 1879, from B. C. Mosby, Amherst County, Virginia, to F. Beattie asking Beattie to recommend a criminal lawyer. Beattie forwarded that letter to Payne, stating that he recommended Payne. (Folder 2)
- Letter, 4 January 1880, from B. C. Mosby, Amherst County, to Payne, concerning his difficulties with a classmate and the legal troubles stemming from that. (Folder 3)
- Letter, 1 July 1880, from Jefferson Davis, Harrison County, Mississippi, to Payne thanking him for his letter, and asking Payne to thank Colonel Smith for his "assault" upon an editor who had maligned Davis. (Folder 3)
- Telegram, 23 August 1880, from Robert S. Smith, Danville, Virginia, to Payne stating that "Major Glass is in Petersburg." (Folder 3)
- Telegram, 23 August 1880, from R. H. Glass, Petersburg, to Payne providing information on [A. W. Jones]. (Folder 3)
- Letter, 23 August [1880?], from Payne to [A. W. Jones], challenging him to a duel for remarks that appeared in the Richmond Dispatch. (Folder 3)
- Telegram, 24 August 1880, from John J. Wilkinson, Danville, to Payne stating that [A. W. Jones]'s address is unknown. (Folder 3)
- Telegram, 24 August 1880, from Payne, Warrenton, to telegraph operator at Orkney Springs, Virginia, asking is a dispatch from B. P. Green had been delivered to Colonel A. W. Jones. (Folder 3)
- Letter, [24 August 1880], from B. P. Green to Payne enclosing a telegram from the Orkney Spring operator stating that a previous message had been delivered. (Folder 3)
- Telegram, 24 August 1880, from John J. Wilkinson, Danville, to Payne stating that A. W. Jones is booked to speak at the Madison County Court House soon. (Folder 3)
- Telegram, 24 August 1880, from A. W. Jones, Orkney Springs, to Bernard P. Green stating that he has an appointment on Thursday and will be in Washington D.C. on Friday. (Folder 3)
- Letter, 24 August 1880, from Payne, Washington D.C., to A. W. Jones concerning remarks by Jones published in the Richmond Dispatch, which Payne considers "injurious." (Folder 3)
- Copy of letter, 24 August 1880, from Payne, Washington D.C., to A. W. Jones concerning remarks in a speech made by Jones and published in the Richmond Dispatch, which Payne considers "injurious." (Folder 3)
- Letter, 24 August 1880, from A. W. Jones, Orkney Springs, to Payne denying he made the statement about which Payne complains. (Folder 3)
- Letter, 24 August 1880, from R. H. Glass, Danville, to Payne concerning A. W. Jones's speech and his character. (Folder 3)
- Letter, 25 August 1880, from Bernard P. Green, Alexandria, to A. W. Jones asking when and where Jones will be in Washington. (Folder 3)
- Telegram, 26 August 1880, from A. W. Jones, Orkney Springs, to Bernard P. Green stating that he will be at the Riggs House on Saturday afternoon. (Folder 3)
- Telegram, 26 August 1880, from C. E. F. Payne, Warrenton, to Payne, Alexandria, stating that a telegram has arrived and asking if he should bring it this evening. (Folder 3)
- Telegram, 26 August 1880, from Bernard P. Green, Alexandria, to C. E. F. Payne, Warrenton, telling him to bring the telegram tonight. (Folder 3)
- Letter, 28 August 1880, from A. W. Jones, Washington, to Payne stating that he never mentioned Payne's name in a speech and sent a card to the Richmond Dispatch saying the same for publication. (Folder 3)
- Copy of letter, 28 August 1880, from A. W. Jones, Washington, to Payne stating that he never mentioned Payne's name in a speech and sent a card to the Richmond Dispatch saying the same for publication. (Folder 3)
- Letter, 28 August 1880, from Payne, Washington, to A. W. Jones stating that he is satisfied with Jones's explanation. (Folder 3)
- Copy of letter, 28 August 1880, from Payne, Washington, to A. W. Jones stating that he is satisfied with Jones's explanation. (Folder 3)
- Telegram, 30 August 1880, from H. K. Ellyson of the Richmond Dispatch to Payne stating that he has received Jones's card and that it will be published in the following day's paper. (Folder 3)
- Letter, 1 September 1880, from Payne, Warrenton, to A. W. Jones stating that Jones' letter was satisfactory and had it and Jones's card to the Dispatch published in the Solid South. (Folder 3)
- Letter, 28 March 1881, from Samuel Simpson, Fairfax, to John D. Payne complaining that Payne had defrauded him. (Folder 3)
- Letter, 9 April 1881, from William H. Payne, Warrenton, to Samuel Simpson concerning his complaint that John D. Payne had defrauded him. Payne notes that John D. Payne is dead and adds that Simpson is a low character. (Folder 3)
- Copy of letter, 9 April 1881, from William H. Payne, Warrenton, to Samuel Simpson concerning his complaint that John D. Payne had defrauded him. Payne notes that John D. Payne is dead and adds that Simpson is a low character. (Folder 3)
- Letter, 16 April 1881, from Thomas and Carter, lawyers, Fairfax, to Payne, Warrenton, enclosing a letter, 15 April 1881, from Samuel Simpson to Thomas and Carter concerning his earlier letter to John D. Payne. Includes notes, 20 April 1881, by Payne on the matter. (Folder 3)
- Letter, 19 April 1881, from James M. Love, Fairfax, to Payne concerning Samuel Simpson and the deaths of his wife and daughter. (Folder 3)
- Handbill, [August 1881], "To the Public" concerning the controversy between Robert Campbell and James C. Scott and the duel that was planned. (Folder 3)
- Telegram, 19 September 1881, from James M. Wise, Richmond, to Payne, Richmond, asking if it would be possible to meet friends. (Folder 3)
- Letter, 23 September 1881, from Peyton Wise, Richmond, to Payne, Warrenton, thanking him for his assistance during a duel between Wise and Judge L. L. Lewis of Richmond which took place outside of Warrenton. Includes notes by Eppa Hunton concerning the duel. (Folder 3)
- Letter, 15 October 1881, from Jubal Early, Lynchburg, to Payne commenting on his relationship to William Mahone. Includes a clipping containing a report of Early's speech on Mahone delivered in Richmond, paper not known. (Folder 3)
- Letter, 28 September 1882, from Jubal Early, Lynchburg, to Payne regarding John W. Daniel. (Folder 3)
- Clipping, 1883, recounting a duel between Dr. Daniel Johnson and Thomas F. Jones, both of North Carolina. The duel took place near Bladensburg, Maryland in 1846. The story was published in the Washington Evening Star. (Folder 3)
- Clipping, 3 July 1883, concerning the duel between Richard F. Beirne, editor of the Richmond State, and William C. Elam, editor of the Richmond Whig, which took place outside Waynseboro, Virginia. Clipping is from the Richmond State. (Folder 3)
- Clipping, 5 July 1883, concerning the duel between Richard F. Beirne and William C. Elam. Published in the Warrenton Virginian. (Folder 3)
- Letter, 6 July 1883, from Payne, Warrenton, to Courtland Smith apologizing for his comments about Smith's friend Aleck Hunter. (Folder 3)
- Letter, 23 December 1883, from J. C. Gibson, Culpeper Court House, Virginia, to Payne concerning his dispute with James A. Frazier. (Folder 3)
- Letter, 27 December 1883, Letter, J. C. Gibson, Culpeper, to Payne stating that he had received a letter of explanation from James A. Frazier and was going to let the matter rest. (Folder 3)
- Clipping, 1884, "Messrs. McCarty and Wise" and "To the Public" concerning Page McCarty and John S. Wise, both published in the Lynchburg Campaign. (Folder 3)
- Letter, 11 March 1884, from Page McCarty, Richmond, to Payne concerning McCarty's difficulties with William Mahone and his party. (Folder 3)
- Letter, 21 December 1885, from H. B. McClellan, Lexington, Kentucky, to Payne, Warrenton, concerning his book on the Civil War and includes the reports, 24 July and 1 August 1861, of Thomas T. Munford and R. C. W. Radford concerning their commands during the first battle of Manassas. (Folder 3)
- Letter, 16 September 1886, from H. B. McClellan, Lexington, Kentucky, to Payne asking Payne's opinion on a meeting between veterans of the Army of Northern Virginia and of the Army of the Potomac at Gettysburg, 1-3 July 1888. Includes Payne's note concerning his reply that he would not participate. (Folder 3)
- Letter, 31 October 1886, from Governor Fitzhugh Lee, Richmond, to Payne concerning personal news. (Folder 3)
- Letter, 1 October 1892 from Thomas Ellett, secretary o fthe Virginia Division of the Association of the Army of Northern Virginia, Richmond, to Payne concerning the speaker for the upcoming meeting of the association. Includes a note by Payne. (Folder 4)
- Letter, 24 October 1892, from Thomas Ellett, Richmond, to Payne sending notice for a meeting of the officers, executive committee, and advisory committee of the Virginia Division of the Association of the Army of Northern Virginia. (Folder 4)
- Letter, 27 October 1892, from Thomas Ellett, Richmond, to Payne reporting the meeting of the Virginia Division of the Association of the Army of Northern Virginia, including the election of officers. (Folder 4)
- Speech, 4 April 1893 "Remarks of William H. Payne at the Memorial Meeting of the Fauquier Bar in Honor of Captain Alexander Dixon Payne." (Folder 4)
- Member certificate, 7 December 1895, of W. H. Payne in the Veteran Cavalry Association, Army of Northern Virginia, by Fitz Lee, President. (Folder 4)
- Letter, 18 January 1903, from Mary Amelia Smith, President of the Black Horse chapter, United Daughters of the Confederacy, to Payne awarding him the UDC Confederate Cross of Honor. (Folder 4)
- Clipping, [8 April 1904], about the Black Horse Troop written by William H. Payne and originally published in 1899. It was reprinted in the Leesburg Washingtonian Mirror. (Folder 4)
- Clippings, 29-31 March 1904, on the death of General William Henry Fitzhugh Payne from various Virginia Newspapers. Also includes a poem titled "A Good Old Rebel." (Folder 4)
- Narrative, 1910, by Mary Elizabeth Winston Payne entitled "Search for My Wounded Husband" detailing her hunt for William H. Payne after his wounding at the battle of Williamsburg on 5 May 1862. (Folder 4)
- Letter, 28 September no year, from Payne to J. H. Williams objecting to comments made by Williams. (Folder 4)
- Clipping, no date, detailing an anti-duelling association formed in Camden, South Carolina. (Folder 4)
- Clipping, no date, concerning famous Mississippi duels, including one between Charles E. Wright and Charles Scott. (Folder 4)